<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Mauricio Zambrano-Bigiarini</title>
    <description>A web site about my research interests, projects and ongoing activities.
</description>
    <link>http://hzambran.github.io/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://hzambran.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Thu, 04 Aug 2016 01:27:47 -0400</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 04 Aug 2016 01:27:47 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.5.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>El año 2015 batió récords de fenómenos climáticos extremos (El Mercurio)</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;El año 2015 marcó una temporada de lluvias más abundantes que el promedio, provocando graves &lt;strong&gt;inundaciones&lt;/strong&gt;. Severas &lt;strong&gt;sequías&lt;/strong&gt; afectaron superficies casi &lt;strong&gt;dos veces mayores en 2015 que en el año anterior&lt;/strong&gt; (14%, contra 8% en 2014).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Las aguas más calientes agravaron la propagación de algas, que afectaron el 2015 una importante región del Pacífico norte, desde California hasta la Columbia Británica, en Canadá.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;calor-y-lluvias&quot;&gt;Calor y lluvias&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;En el caso sudamericano, El Niño influyó en las condiciones climáticas durante todo el 2015. La &lt;strong&gt;temperatura del aire aumentó por sobre el promedio&lt;/strong&gt; en la mayor parte del continente, lo que generó condiciones más secas que el promedio en el norte y más húmedas en el sur, especialmente Chile y Argentina.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No obstante, se presentó un otoño e invierno más calurosos de lo habitual. En Argentina fue el invierno más caliente desde que se tienen registros, con un aumento de la media por sobre los 3ºC. En contraste, un aumento de los sistemas frontales y de la nubosidad produjo en Chile y, particularmente, en Argentina el más frío octubre desde que se tienen registros.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;En marzo 2015, una &lt;strong&gt;anormal lluvia&lt;/strong&gt; sorprendió a las secas regiones de &lt;strong&gt;Atacama&lt;/strong&gt; y &lt;strong&gt;Antofagasta&lt;/strong&gt;. En esta última ciudad, entre el 25 y el 26 de ese mes cayeron 24,4 milímetros de agua, cuando el promedio anual es de 1,7. En agosto y diciembre, las precipitaciones intensas se presentaron en Argentina y Paraguay, generando inundaciones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information please visit the website: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cr2.cl/el-ano-pasado-batio-records-de-fenomenos-climaticos-extremos-el-mercurio/&quot;&gt;http://www.cr2.cl/el-ano-pasado-batio-records-de-fenomenos-climaticos-extremos-el-mercurio/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 03 Aug 2016 19:59:59 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://hzambran.github.io/drought/climate_change/2016/08/03/Year_2015_hottest_on_record_CR2.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://hzambran.github.io/drought/climate_change/2016/08/03/Year_2015_hottest_on_record_CR2.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>drought</category>
        
        <category>climate_change</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>PhD summer school Remote Sensing applications for Water Accounting</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Water accounting&lt;/strong&gt; is a fundamental basis to understand water availability and demands and the related benefits and efficiencies are related to water uses. While the fundamental data needed for establishing water accounts is often missing, Remote Sensing can contribute to fill the data gaps.
With this course PhD students and staff at ITT will become familiar with the application of Remote Sensing to derive information on precipitation, evapotranspiration and land cover - three essential information elements for water accounts.
Dr. Raul Vicens from Universidade Federal Fluminense de Brasil will introduce the basic techinques of Remote Sensing using the software SPRING and introduce to derive land cover information from products such as Landsat. &lt;strong&gt;Dr. Mauricio Zambrano-Bigiarini&lt;/strong&gt; from &lt;a href=&quot;www.ufro.cl&quot;&gt;Universidad de la Frontera&lt;/a&gt;, Chile, will focus on the use of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.r-project.org/&quot;&gt;R&lt;/a&gt; software to derive Precipitation estimates from products such as TRMM. Finally Dr Islam Sabry from the National Water Research Center, Egypt will introduce the use of satellite based estimates for evapotranspiration data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/posts/2016-07-20-RS_PhD_course_at_ITT.png&quot; alt=&quot;example of analysis&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 20 Jul 2016 19:59:59 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://hzambran.github.io/remote_sensing/precipitation/r/training/2016/07/20/Training_on_RS_at_ITT.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://hzambran.github.io/remote_sensing/precipitation/r/training/2016/07/20/Training_on_RS_at_ITT.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>remote_sensing</category>
        
        <category>precipitation</category>
        
        <category>r</category>
        
        <category>training</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Research and Education Week on the Water, Energy and Food Security Nexus</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.water-energy-food-nexus.info&quot;&gt;Water-Energy-Food Security Nexus&lt;/a&gt; (WEF Nexus) is currently a highly important debate in environmental policy with expected implications for priorities in research, education and international cooperation. Increasing demands for water, energy and food together with external and internal change drivers on current natural resources use patterns make the Nexus idea crucial to understand the multiple resource use interlinkages. 
The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tt.th-koeln.de/&quot;&gt;ITT&lt;/a&gt; invited partners from current Nexus-related projects for an international gathering from the 11th until the 15th of July 2016. The &lt;strong&gt;Nexus Research and Education Week&lt;/strong&gt; invited also external presenters and students into the discussion on how to address together many of the key interlinkages like sustainable land and water management practices, climate related risks in terms of droughts and extremes or increasing resource use efficiencies along river basins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/posts/2016-07-14-WEF_Nexus_Group-768x512.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;WEF_Nexus_Group&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the Nexus Week, the professor &lt;strong&gt;Mauricio Zambrano-Bigiarini&lt;/strong&gt; along with international partners presented their case studies from related projects as &lt;em&gt;nexus laboratories&lt;/em&gt; useful for enhancing educational contents and outlining future collaborative research activities. International experts and young researchers were involved in providing insights on the WEF Nexus topic from ongoing research and and outlining further research demand. 
Different case studies with WEF-Nexus related topics at river basin scale were presented from countries such as Jordan, Sudan, Ethiopia, Egypt, Pakistan, &lt;strong&gt;Chile&lt;/strong&gt;, Ecuador, Costa Rica and Colombia and also larger scales as the Mekong, the Nile and Paraiba do Sul region or even global scale. The Nexus Week aimed at expanding the network of partners related to Nexus topics and interdisciplinary regional and basin planning initiatives and offered an opportunity as an exchange platform. 
During additional side events of the Nexus Week, the participants developed new project ideas and exchanged experiences on integrated water basin management during a visit to the International Commission for the Protection of the Rhine. Further more, different Nexus products were presented and prepared for further development in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information about the project please visit the website: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.water-energy-food-nexus.info&quot;&gt;http://www.water-energy-food-nexus.info&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 15 Jul 2016 19:59:59 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://hzambran.github.io/wef-nexus/2016/07/15/NexusWeek_at_ITT.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://hzambran.github.io/wef-nexus/2016/07/15/NexusWeek_at_ITT.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>wef-nexus</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>2015 was the warmest year ever recorded on Earth (NASA-NOAA)</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2015 was the warmest year ever recorded on Earth&lt;/strong&gt;, and it was not even close.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On January 20, 2016, scientists from NASA and the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA) released their analyses of surface temperatures for the past year. 
The NASA team found that globally averaged temperatures from January through December 2015 were &lt;strong&gt;0.87 degrees Celsius above the norm&lt;/strong&gt; (defined as a 1951-1980 base period). The previous record—set last year—was 0.74°C above the norm. 
For the planet, &lt;strong&gt;2015 was more than a full degree Celsius warmer than temperatures in 1880&lt;/strong&gt;, when consistent record-keeping began.
Working independently, NOAA researchers found 2015 to be 0.90°C above the 1901-2000 average. According to their analysis, 2015 was the second warmest year on record for the continental United States, Africa, and Europe. &lt;strong&gt;It was the warmest year for Asia and South America&lt;/strong&gt;. Globally, new monthly temperature records were set in every month except January and April.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2015 temperature record continues a long-term warming trend that has largely been driven by increased carbon dioxide and other greenhouse gases that humans have emitted into the atmosphere. Most of the warming has occurred in the past 35 years, with &lt;strong&gt;15 of the 16 warmest years on record occurring since 2001&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;enso&quot;&gt;ENSO&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that while El Niño conditions dominated the Pacific Ocean for most of 2015, &lt;strong&gt;it was not officially an El Niño year in strict climatological terms&lt;/strong&gt; because ocean conditions did not manifest themselves until April 2015. 
In the past, the highest global temperature records were often set in El Niño years, which suggests that 2016—with El Niño going strong as of mid-January—appears likely to be another very warm year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;2015 was remarkable even in the context of the ongoing El Niño&lt;/em&gt; said NASA GISS Director Gavin Schmidt. &lt;em&gt;Last year’s temperatures had an assist from El Niño, but it is the cumulative effect of the long-term trend that has resulted in the record warming that we are seeing.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Climate change is the challenge of our generation&lt;/em&gt;”, said NASA Administrator Charles Bolden. &lt;em&gt;Today’s announcement not only underscores how critical NASA’s Earth observation program is, it is a key data point that should make policymakers stand up and take notice. &lt;strong&gt;Now is the time to act on climate&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information please visit the website: &lt;a href=&quot;http://earthobservatory.nasa.gov/IOTD/view.php?id=87359&quot;&gt;http://earthobservatory.nasa.gov/IOTD/view.php?id=87359&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2016 20:59:59 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>http://hzambran.github.io/climate_change/2016/02/01/Year_2015_was_the_warmest_year_ever_recorded_on_Earth_NASA.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://hzambran.github.io/climate_change/2016/02/01/Year_2015_was_the_warmest_year_ever_recorded_on_Earth_NASA.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>climate_change</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
