<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Mauricio Zambrano-Bigiarini</title>
    <description>A web site about my research interests, projects and ongoing activities.
</description>
    <link>http://hzambran.github.io/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://hzambran.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sun, 21 May 2017 12:13:55 -0400</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 21 May 2017 12:13:55 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.2.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Fondecyt Regular 1171560 selected in 2017 competition !</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The proyect 1171560 entitled “&lt;em&gt;Assessing spatio-temporal impacts of global change on water and biomass production processes at catchment scale: a synergistic approach based on remote sensing and coupled hydrological models to improve sustainable management of forest ecosystems&lt;/em&gt;” was &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.conicyt.cl/fondecyt/files/2016/03/Propuesta-Adjudicacion-Fondecyt-Regular-2017.pdf&quot;&gt;selected&lt;/a&gt; in the 2017 Chilean competition for “Fondecyt Regular” proyects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This proposal is a collaborative effort born completly within the  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cr2.cl/&quot;&gt;Center for Climate and Resilience Research (CR2)&lt;/a&gt; FONDAP, where the principal investigator (PI) Mauricio Galleguillos and me (Co-PI) are working. This proyect started as a truly interdisciplinary idea, and a research visit of the PI to Temuco was the perfect ocassion to discuss about the main research question, methodology and expected outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The recent fires that are affecting Chile since January 2017, are important evidence that the outcomes of this project might have important societal impacts.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 07 Feb 2017 13:51:00 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>http://hzambran.github.io/fondecyt-1171560/2017/02/07/Fondecyt_Regular_con_MG-Accepted.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://hzambran.github.io/fondecyt-1171560/2017/02/07/Fondecyt_Regular_con_MG-Accepted.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>fondecyt-1171560</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Article on satellite-based rainfall estimates over Chile accepted for publication in HESS</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The article &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hydrol-earth-syst-sci-discuss.net/hess-2016-453/&quot;&gt;“Temporal and spatial evaluation of satellite-based rainfall estimates across the complex topographical and climatic gradients of Chile”&lt;/a&gt; was accepted yesterday (January 30th, 2017) for publication in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hydrology-and-earth-system-sciences.net/about/aims_and_scope.html&quot;&gt;Hydrology and Earth System Sciences&lt;/a&gt; journal (HESS).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This work exhaustively evaluate -for the first time- the suitability of seven state-of-the-art satellite-based rainfall estimates (SRE) over the complex topography and diverse climatic gradients of Chile. Several indices of performance are used for different time scales and elevation zones. Our analysis revealed which products are in best with ground based observations of precipitation and which indices of performance suitable to capture mismatches in shape, magnitude, variability and intensity of precipitation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jan 2017 20:59:59 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>http://hzambran.github.io/remote-sensing/precipitation/fondecyt-11150861/2017/01/30/HESS_article_on_SRE_accepted.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://hzambran.github.io/remote-sensing/precipitation/fondecyt-11150861/2017/01/30/HESS_article_on_SRE_accepted.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>remote-sensing</category>
        
        <category>precipitation</category>
        
        <category>fondecyt-11150861</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>2016: Hottest Year on Record</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Earth’s 2016 surface temperatures were the warmest since modern recordkeeping began in 1880, according to independent analyses by NASA and the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Globally-averaged temperatures in 2016 were 0.99 degrees Celsius (1.78 degrees Fahrenheit) warmer than the mid-20th century mean. This makes &lt;strong&gt;2016 the third year in a row&lt;/strong&gt; to set a new record for global average surface temperatures. Since the start of the 21st century, the annual global temperature record has been broken five times (2005, 2010, 2014, 2015, and 2016) &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.noaa.gov/stories/2016-marks-three-consecutive-years-of-record-warmth-for-globe&quot;&gt;NOAA&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the warming occurred in the past 35 years, with 16 of the 17 warmest years on record occurring since 2001. Not only was 2016 the warmest year on record, but eight of the 12 months that make up the year - from January through September, with the exception of June - were the warmest on record for those respective months. October, November, and December of 2016 were the second warmest of those months on record - in all three cases, behind records set in 2015 &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.npr.org/sections/thetwo-way/2017/01/18/510405739/2016-was-the-hottest-year-yet-scientists-declare&quot;&gt;NPR, Jan 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The warming was truly global. &lt;em&gt;“Some part of every continent, and some part of every major ocean basin was warmest on record”&lt;/em&gt; Arndt says, adding that in the United States, only Georgia and Alaska had record-setting warmth but &lt;em&gt;“pretty much the entire country was above normal, and well above normal.”&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.npr.org/sections/thetwo-way/2017/01/18/510405739/2016-was-the-hottest-year-yet-scientists-declare&quot;&gt;NPR, Jan 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The long-term warming is driven almost entirely by greenhouse gases”&lt;/em&gt; Arndt says. &lt;em&gt;“We’ve seen a warming trend related to greenhouse gases for four, five, six decades now”&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.npr.org/sections/thetwo-way/2017/01/18/510405739/2016-was-the-hottest-year-yet-scientists-declare&quot;&gt;NPR, Jan 2017&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two graphs that shows the time evolution of globally-averaged temperatues are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nasa.gov/sites/default/files/thumbnails/image/2016gistempupdateblack.gif&quot;&gt;NASA&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2017/01/18/science/earth/2016-hottest-year-on-record.html?_r=0&quot;&gt;New York Times&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information please visit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nasa.gov/press-release/nasa-noaa-data-show-2016-warmest-year-on-record-globally&quot;&gt;https://www.nasa.gov/press-release/nasa-noaa-data-show-2016-warmest-year-on-record-globally&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jan 2017 20:59:59 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>http://hzambran.github.io/droughts/climate-change/2017/01/19/Year_2016_hottest_on_record.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://hzambran.github.io/droughts/climate-change/2017/01/19/Year_2016_hottest_on_record.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>droughts</category>
        
        <category>climate-change</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Expected changes in precipitation and temperature by 2050 (La Tercera)</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A recent study, delivered in July 2016, projected that by 2050 Santiago will have the most extreme variation in temperature of all regional capitals, with 2.7°C, which is 14% higher compared to today. In winter, the increase will be 1.7%, representing an increase of 19%, while precipitation will be reduced by 55 millimeters (mm), 15% less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other regional capitals, as Arica and Copiapó, extreme temperatures rise about 2.2°C are also expected for each summer, but it will be Arica where the temperature will rise more in winter, with 2.5° C.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information please visit: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.latercera.com/noticia/tendencias/2016/09/659-697259-9-informe-climatico-dice-que-a-2050-temperatura-en-santiago-subira-27c-y-lluvias.shtml&quot;&gt;Informe climático dice que a 2050 temperatura en Santiago subirá 2,7°C y lluvias caerán 15%&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 21 Aug 2016 20:59:59 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>http://hzambran.github.io/droughts/climate-change/2016/08/21/Temperature_and_precipitation_changes_by_2050.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://hzambran.github.io/droughts/climate-change/2016/08/21/Temperature_and_precipitation_changes_by_2050.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>droughts</category>
        
        <category>climate-change</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Megadrought expands to southern Chile (La Tercera)</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Today the country is experiencing one of the longest and most geographically extensive droughts in its history, which has nearly eight years in some sectors, and extends from the Coquimbo to the La Araucania region. Experts estimate that in the future these cycles would increase. According to an analysis by the  Center for Climate and Resilience Research (CR2) in 2015, these mega-droughts will become more common, occurring in Chile every 20 years by 2050 if emissions continue to increase greenhouse gases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To date, 17 of the 22 stations of the Meteorological Direction of Chile (DMC) present below normal precipitation amounts. Coyhaique (45ºS) is the one with the most extreme situation. There, the precipitation is around 220 mm, far from normal to date according to the climatological period 1981-2010, which is 884.5 mm, resulting in a deficit of 75%. The level of rainfall is the lowest registration for the area (starting in 1960), although it is projected that in the next three months rains occur within the normal range indicates Catalina Cortes, meteorologist at DMC. However, it should end the year in deficit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information please visit: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.latercera.com/noticia/tendencias/2016/08/659-693246-9-megasequia-se-expande-hacia-el-sur-del-pais.shtml&quot;&gt;Megasequía se expande hacia el sur del país&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 21 Aug 2016 20:59:59 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>http://hzambran.github.io/droughts/climate-change/2016/08/21/Megasequia-se_expande_hacia_el_sur.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://hzambran.github.io/droughts/climate-change/2016/08/21/Megasequia-se_expande_hacia_el_sur.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>droughts</category>
        
        <category>climate-change</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Drought in Puyehue and Rupanco lakes (SoyChile.cl)</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;After &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.australosorno.cl/impresa/2016/06/14/full/cuerpo-principal/2/?utm_source=pagina&amp;amp;utm_campaign=soychile&amp;amp;utm_medium=3&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Austral de Osorno&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; revealed the worrying decline in the water levels of Llanquihue Lake in the  surrounding of Puerto Octay, it was found that is not the only lake basin of the region affected by the lack of rainfall that experts have attributed to climate change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is because now the Rupanco and Puyehue lakes in the province of Osorno, have also shown and alarming and disturbing situation. In the first case, locals say that in some sectors the beach has increased from 20 to 200 meters, and in areas normally covered by water can now move on foot or by vehicle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A similar situation occurs in the Rupanco, where residents also confirm that there is an obvious decline in its water levels, exposing larger portions of land. *This is the year where I’ve seen the worst shortage of water in the lake. It has fallen very little rain. Luckily our pastures are still green, but the lake has suffered,” said a local farmer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information please visit: &lt;a href=&quot;[http://www.soychile.cl/Osorno/Sociedad/2016/06/16/399942/No-es-solo-el-Llanquihue-asi-lucen-los-lagos-Puyehue-y-Rupanco-por-la-sequia.aspx]&quot;&gt;No es sólo el Llanquihue: así lucen los lagos Puyehue y Rupanco por la sequía&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 21 Aug 2016 20:59:59 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>http://hzambran.github.io/droughts/climate-change/2016/08/21/Drought_in_Puyehue_and_Rupanco_lakes.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://hzambran.github.io/droughts/climate-change/2016/08/21/Drought_in_Puyehue_and_Rupanco_lakes.html</guid>
        
        <category>droughts</category>
        
        <category>climate-change</category>
        
        
        <category>droughts</category>
        
        <category>climate-change</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>July 2016 was world's hottest month since records began, says Nasa (The Guardian)</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Nasa’s results, which combine sea-surface temperature and air temperature on land, show July 2016 was 10th month in a row to break monthly temperature record&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the string of hottest months continues, 2016 is &lt;em&gt;virtually certain&lt;/em&gt; to be the &lt;strong&gt;hottest year on record&lt;/strong&gt;, says David Karoly, a climate scientist from the University of Melbourne.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last month was the hottest month in recorded history, beating the record set just 12 months before and continuing the long string of monthly records, according to the latest Nasa data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The past nine months have set temperature records for their respective months and the trend continued this month to make 10 in a row, according to Nasa. &lt;strong&gt;July broke the absolute record for hottest month since records began in 1880&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similar data from the US National Oceanographic and Atmospheric Administration (Noaa) said the past 14 months have broken the temperature record for each month, but it hasn’t released its figures for July yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information please visit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/environment/2016/aug/16/july-2016-was-worlds-hottest-month-since-records-began-says-nasa&quot;&gt;July 2016 was world’s hottest month since records began, says Nasa&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 20 Aug 2016 20:59:59 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>http://hzambran.github.io/climate-change/2016/08/20/Hottest_July_on_record.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://hzambran.github.io/climate-change/2016/08/20/Hottest_July_on_record.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>climate-change</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>El año 2015 batió récords de fenómenos climáticos extremos (El Mercurio)</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;El año 2015 marcó una temporada de lluvias más abundantes que el promedio, provocando graves &lt;strong&gt;inundaciones&lt;/strong&gt;. Severas &lt;strong&gt;sequías&lt;/strong&gt; afectaron superficies casi &lt;strong&gt;dos veces mayores en 2015 que en el año anterior&lt;/strong&gt; (14%, contra 8% en 2014).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Las aguas más calientes agravaron la propagación de algas, que afectaron el 2015 una importante región del Pacífico norte, desde California hasta la Columbia Británica, en Canadá.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;calor-y-lluvias&quot;&gt;Calor y lluvias&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;En el caso sudamericano, El Niño influyó en las condiciones climáticas durante todo el 2015. La &lt;strong&gt;temperatura del aire aumentó por sobre el promedio&lt;/strong&gt; en la mayor parte del continente, lo que generó condiciones más secas que el promedio en el norte y más húmedas en el sur, especialmente Chile y Argentina.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No obstante, se presentó un otoño e invierno más calurosos de lo habitual. En Argentina fue el invierno más caliente desde que se tienen registros, con un aumento de la media por sobre los 3ºC. En contraste, un aumento de los sistemas frontales y de la nubosidad produjo en Chile y, particularmente, en Argentina el más frío octubre desde que se tienen registros.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;En marzo 2015, una &lt;strong&gt;anormal lluvia&lt;/strong&gt; sorprendió a las secas regiones de &lt;strong&gt;Atacama&lt;/strong&gt; y &lt;strong&gt;Antofagasta&lt;/strong&gt;. En esta última ciudad, entre el 25 y el 26 de ese mes cayeron 24,4 milímetros de agua, cuando el promedio anual es de 1,7. En agosto y diciembre, las precipitaciones intensas se presentaron en Argentina y Paraguay, generando inundaciones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information please visit the website: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cr2.cl/el-ano-pasado-batio-records-de-fenomenos-climaticos-extremos-el-mercurio/&quot;&gt;http://www.cr2.cl/el-ano-pasado-batio-records-de-fenomenos-climaticos-extremos-el-mercurio/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 03 Aug 2016 19:59:59 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://hzambran.github.io/droughts/climate-change/2016/08/03/Year_2015_hottest_on_record_CR2.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://hzambran.github.io/droughts/climate-change/2016/08/03/Year_2015_hottest_on_record_CR2.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>droughts</category>
        
        <category>climate-change</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>PhD summer school Remote Sensing applications for Water Accounting</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Water accounting&lt;/strong&gt; is a fundamental basis to understand water availability and demands and the related benefits and efficiencies are related to water uses. While the fundamental data needed for establishing water accounts is often missing, Remote Sensing can contribute to fill the data gaps.
With this course PhD students and staff at ITT will become familiar with the application of Remote Sensing to derive information on precipitation, evapotranspiration and land cover - three essential information elements for water accounts.
Dr. Raul Vicens from Universidade Federal Fluminense de Brasil will introduce the basic techinques of Remote Sensing using the software SPRING and introduce to derive land cover information from products such as Landsat. &lt;strong&gt;Dr. Mauricio Zambrano-Bigiarini&lt;/strong&gt; from &lt;a href=&quot;www.ufro.cl&quot;&gt;Universidad de la Frontera&lt;/a&gt;, Chile, will focus on the use of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.r-project.org/&quot;&gt;R&lt;/a&gt; software to derive Precipitation estimates from products such as TRMM. Finally Dr Islam Sabry from the National Water Research Center, Egypt will introduce the use of satellite based estimates for evapotranspiration data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/posts/2016-07-20-RS_PhD_course_at_ITT.png&quot; alt=&quot;example of analysis&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 20 Jul 2016 19:59:59 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://hzambran.github.io/remote-sensing/precipitation/r/training/2016/07/20/Training_on_RS_at_ITT.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://hzambran.github.io/remote-sensing/precipitation/r/training/2016/07/20/Training_on_RS_at_ITT.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>remote-sensing</category>
        
        <category>precipitation</category>
        
        <category>r</category>
        
        <category>training</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Research and Education Week on the Water, Energy and Food Security Nexus</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.water-energy-food-nexus.info&quot;&gt;Water-Energy-Food Security Nexus&lt;/a&gt; (WEF Nexus) is currently a highly important debate in environmental policy with expected implications for priorities in research, education and international cooperation. Increasing demands for water, energy and food together with external and internal change drivers on current natural resources use patterns make the Nexus idea crucial to understand the multiple resource use interlinkages. 
The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tt.th-koeln.de/&quot;&gt;ITT&lt;/a&gt; invited partners from current Nexus-related projects for an international gathering from the 11th until the 15th of July 2016. The &lt;strong&gt;Nexus Research and Education Week&lt;/strong&gt; invited also external presenters and students into the discussion on how to address together many of the key interlinkages like sustainable land and water management practices, climate related risks in terms of droughts and extremes or increasing resource use efficiencies along river basins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/posts/2016-07-14-WEF_Nexus_Group-768x512.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;WEF_Nexus_Group&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the Nexus Week, the professor &lt;strong&gt;Mauricio Zambrano-Bigiarini&lt;/strong&gt; along with international partners presented their case studies from related projects as &lt;em&gt;nexus laboratories&lt;/em&gt; useful for enhancing educational contents and outlining future collaborative research activities. International experts and young researchers were involved in providing insights on the WEF Nexus topic from ongoing research and and outlining further research demand. 
Different case studies with WEF-Nexus related topics at river basin scale were presented from countries such as Jordan, Sudan, Ethiopia, Egypt, Pakistan, &lt;strong&gt;Chile&lt;/strong&gt;, Ecuador, Costa Rica and Colombia and also larger scales as the Mekong, the Nile and Paraiba do Sul region or even global scale. The Nexus Week aimed at expanding the network of partners related to Nexus topics and interdisciplinary regional and basin planning initiatives and offered an opportunity as an exchange platform. 
During additional side events of the Nexus Week, the participants developed new project ideas and exchanged experiences on integrated water basin management during a visit to the International Commission for the Protection of the Rhine. Further more, different Nexus products were presented and prepared for further development in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information about the project please visit the website: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.water-energy-food-nexus.info&quot;&gt;http://www.water-energy-food-nexus.info&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 15 Jul 2016 19:59:59 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://hzambran.github.io/wef-nexus/2016/07/15/NexusWeek_at_ITT.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://hzambran.github.io/wef-nexus/2016/07/15/NexusWeek_at_ITT.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>WEF-Nexus</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
