<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Mauricio Zambrano-Bigiarini</title>
    <description>A web site about my research interests, projects and ongoing activities.
</description>
    <link>http://hzambran.github.io/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://hzambran.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sat, 26 May 2018 00:34:43 -0400</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 26 May 2018 00:34:43 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.2.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Article on satellite-based rainfall estimates over Latin America accepted for publication in Atmospheric Research</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The article &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.atmosres.2018.05.011&quot;&gt;“Temporal and spatial evaluation of satellite rainfall estimates over different regions in Latin-America”&lt;/a&gt; was accepted for publication in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedirect.com/journal/atmospheric-research&quot;&gt;Atmospheric Research&lt;/a&gt; journal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This work exhaustively evaluate six satellite rainfall estimates (TRMM 3B42v7, TRMM 3B42RT, CHIRPSv2, CMORPHv1, PERSIANN-CDR, and MSWEPv2) over three basins in Latin-America (Imperial in Chile, Paraiba do Sul in Brazil, and Magdalena in Colombia). Several continuous and categorical indices of performance are used at daily, monthly and seasonal time scales. Our analysis revealed which products are in beter agreement with ground-based observations of precipitation and if the upscaling procedure, used in CHIRPSv2 and MSWEPv2, affects the evaluation of the SREs performance at different time scales.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 21 May 2018 19:59:59 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://hzambran.github.io/remote-sensing/precipitation/fondecyt-11150861/2018/05/21/AR_article_on_SRE_accepted.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://hzambran.github.io/remote-sensing/precipitation/fondecyt-11150861/2018/05/21/AR_article_on_SRE_accepted.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>remote-sensing</category>
        
        <category>precipitation</category>
        
        <category>fondecyt-11150861</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Short course on use of R for analysing satelite-based rainfall estimates (SREs) in Germany</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;During the first week of May, I gave a short course to postgraduate students of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tt.th-koeln.de/&quot;&gt;Institute for Technology and Resources Management in the Tropics and Subtropics (ITT)&lt;/a&gt; of TH Köln (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.th-koeln.de/&quot;&gt;University of Applied Sciences in Germany&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This course had two parts, the first one was given by the doctoral student Oscar Baez, who was at UFRO last April. The objective of this first part (April 23th to 27th) was to provide students with basic concepts about &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.r-project.org/&quot;&gt;R&lt;/a&gt;, free software environment for statistical computing and graphics, (installation, types of variables, exploratory data analysis, and spatial data management).
 
The second part (May 3rd and 4th) was to introduce participants to the management of time series in R, and the use of it for the analysis of spatio-temporal data, in particular for reading and analysing satelite-based rainfall estimates (SREs), expanding the work “&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.570145&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Using R for analyzing spatio-temporal datasets: a satellite-based precipitation case study&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;” presented at the EGUA 2017 during the last week of April (&lt;a href=&quot;http://meetingorganizer.copernicus.org/EGU2017/EGU2017-18343.pdf&quot;&gt;EGU2017-18343&lt;/a&gt;), which was an oral &lt;a href=&quot;http://egu2017.eu/pico.html&quot;&gt;PICO presentation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This short course is product of the international collaboration with Lars Ribbe and Alexandra Nauditt from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tt.th-koeln.de/&quot;&gt;Institute for Technology and Resources Management in the Tropics and Subtropics (ITT)&lt;/a&gt; of TH Köln (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.th-koeln.de/&quot;&gt;University of Applied Sciences in Germany&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 05 May 2017 20:59:59 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>http://hzambran.github.io/fondecyt-11150861/r/precipitation/remote-sensing/training/2017/05/05/Training_on_RS_at_ITT.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://hzambran.github.io/fondecyt-11150861/r/precipitation/remote-sensing/training/2017/05/05/Training_on_RS_at_ITT.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>fondecyt-11150861</category>
        
        <category>r</category>
        
        <category>precipitation</category>
        
        <category>remote-sensing</category>
        
        <category>training</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Participación en la Conferencia EGU 2017</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;During the last week of April, I presented two works on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://egu2017.eu/information/general_information.html&quot;&gt;European Geosciences Union (EGU) 2017&lt;/a&gt;, the most important scientific event of Earth Sciences in Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first work was &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.570145&quot;&gt;Using R for analyzing spatio-temporal datasets: a satellite-based precipitation case study&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;http://meetingorganizer.copernicus.org/EGU2017/EGU2017-18343.pdf&quot;&gt;EGU2017-18343&lt;/a&gt;), which was an oral &lt;a href=&quot;http://egu2017.eu/pico.html&quot;&gt;PICO presentation&lt;/a&gt; about the use of R, the free software environment for statistical computing and graphics, for analysing different spatio-temporal datasets of precipitation at the Chilean spatail scale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second work was the oral presentation &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.570146&quot;&gt;Assesing the temporal and spatial performance of satellite-based rainfall estimates across the topographical complex and climatic gradients of Chile&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;http://meetingorganizer.copernicus.org/EGU2017/EGU2017-10425.pdf&quot;&gt;EGU2017-10425&lt;/a&gt;), which summarises the main findings about the performance of seven different satellite-based precipitation products over the Chilean territory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both works are the product of the international collaboration with researchers from Germany, Costa Rica and Chile on the use of different satellite-based precipitation products as a complement to current ground-based rainfall measurement networks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spanish version&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Durante la semana del 24 al 28 de Abril, presenté dos trabajos en la conferencia &lt;a href=&quot;http://egu2017.eu/information/general_information.html&quot;&gt;European Geosciences Union (EGU) 2017&lt;/a&gt;, el evento científico más importante de Ciencias de la Tierra en Europa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;El primer trabajo fue &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.570145&quot;&gt;Using R for analyzing spatio-temporal datasets: a satellite-based precipitation case study&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;http://meetingorganizer.copernicus.org/EGU2017/EGU2017-18343.pdf&quot;&gt;EGU2017-18343&lt;/a&gt;), una &lt;a href=&quot;http://egu2017.eu/pico.html&quot;&gt;presentación oral tipo&lt;/a&gt; sobre el uso de R, el ambiente estadístico libre, para el análisis de distintos conjuntos de datos espacio-temporales de precipitaciòn a escala nacional (Chile).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;El segundo trabajo fue la presentación oral &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.570146&quot;&gt;Assesing the temporal and spatial performance of satellite-based rainfall estimates across the topographical complex and climatic gradients of Chile&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;http://meetingorganizer.copernicus.org/EGU2017/EGU2017-10425.pdf&quot;&gt;EGU2017-10425&lt;/a&gt;), la cual resume los principales resultados de una comparación exhaustiva de siete productos satelitales de precipitación sobre el territorio de Chile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ambos trabajos son producto de la colaboración internacional con investigadores de Alemania, Costa Rica y Chile, sobre el uso de distintos productos satelitales de precipitación como complemento a las actuales redes de medición pluviométrica.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 27 Apr 2017 20:59:59 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>http://hzambran.github.io/fondecyt-11150861/r/precipitation/remote-sensing/2017/04/27/EGU2017.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://hzambran.github.io/fondecyt-11150861/r/precipitation/remote-sensing/2017/04/27/EGU2017.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>fondecyt-11150861</category>
        
        <category>r</category>
        
        <category>precipitation</category>
        
        <category>remote-sensing</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Fondecyt Regular 1171560 selected in 2017 competition !</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The proyect 1171560 entitled “&lt;em&gt;Assessing spatio-temporal impacts of global change on water and biomass production processes at catchment scale: a synergistic approach based on remote sensing and coupled hydrological models to improve sustainable management of forest ecosystems&lt;/em&gt;” was &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.conicyt.cl/fondecyt/files/2016/03/Propuesta-Adjudicacion-Fondecyt-Regular-2017.pdf&quot;&gt;selected&lt;/a&gt; in the 2017 Chilean competition for “Fondecyt Regular” proyects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This proposal is a collaborative effort born completly within the  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cr2.cl/&quot;&gt;Center for Climate and Resilience Research (CR2)&lt;/a&gt; FONDAP, where the principal investigator (PI) Mauricio Galleguillos and me (Co-PI) are working. This proyect started as a truly interdisciplinary idea, and a research visit of the PI to Temuco was the perfect ocassion to discuss about the main research question, methodology and expected outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The recent fires that are affecting Chile since January 2017, are important evidence that the outcomes of this project might have important societal impacts.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 07 Feb 2017 13:51:00 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>http://hzambran.github.io/fondecyt-1171560/2017/02/07/Fondecyt_Regular_con_MG-Accepted.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://hzambran.github.io/fondecyt-1171560/2017/02/07/Fondecyt_Regular_con_MG-Accepted.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>fondecyt-1171560</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Article on satellite-based rainfall estimates over Chile accepted for publication in HESS</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The article &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hydrol-earth-syst-sci-discuss.net/hess-2016-453/&quot;&gt;“Temporal and spatial evaluation of satellite-based rainfall estimates across the complex topographical and climatic gradients of Chile”&lt;/a&gt; was accepted yesterday (January 30th, 2017) for publication in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hydrology-and-earth-system-sciences.net/about/aims_and_scope.html&quot;&gt;Hydrology and Earth System Sciences&lt;/a&gt; journal (HESS).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This work exhaustively evaluate -for the first time- the suitability of seven state-of-the-art satellite-based rainfall estimates (SRE) over the complex topography and diverse climatic gradients of Chile. Several indices of performance are used for different time scales and elevation zones. Our analysis revealed which products are in best with ground based observations of precipitation and which indices of performance suitable to capture mismatches in shape, magnitude, variability and intensity of precipitation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jan 2017 20:59:59 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>http://hzambran.github.io/remote-sensing/precipitation/fondecyt-11150861/2017/01/30/HESS_article_on_SRE_accepted.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://hzambran.github.io/remote-sensing/precipitation/fondecyt-11150861/2017/01/30/HESS_article_on_SRE_accepted.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>remote-sensing</category>
        
        <category>precipitation</category>
        
        <category>fondecyt-11150861</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>2016: Hottest Year on Record</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Earth’s 2016 surface temperatures were the warmest since modern recordkeeping began in 1880, according to independent analyses by NASA and the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Globally-averaged temperatures in 2016 were 0.99 degrees Celsius (1.78 degrees Fahrenheit) warmer than the mid-20th century mean. This makes &lt;strong&gt;2016 the third year in a row&lt;/strong&gt; to set a new record for global average surface temperatures. Since the start of the 21st century, the annual global temperature record has been broken five times (2005, 2010, 2014, 2015, and 2016) &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.noaa.gov/stories/2016-marks-three-consecutive-years-of-record-warmth-for-globe&quot;&gt;NOAA&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the warming occurred in the past 35 years, with 16 of the 17 warmest years on record occurring since 2001. Not only was 2016 the warmest year on record, but eight of the 12 months that make up the year - from January through September, with the exception of June - were the warmest on record for those respective months. October, November, and December of 2016 were the second warmest of those months on record - in all three cases, behind records set in 2015 &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.npr.org/sections/thetwo-way/2017/01/18/510405739/2016-was-the-hottest-year-yet-scientists-declare&quot;&gt;NPR, Jan 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The warming was truly global. &lt;em&gt;“Some part of every continent, and some part of every major ocean basin was warmest on record”&lt;/em&gt; Arndt says, adding that in the United States, only Georgia and Alaska had record-setting warmth but &lt;em&gt;“pretty much the entire country was above normal, and well above normal.”&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.npr.org/sections/thetwo-way/2017/01/18/510405739/2016-was-the-hottest-year-yet-scientists-declare&quot;&gt;NPR, Jan 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The long-term warming is driven almost entirely by greenhouse gases”&lt;/em&gt; Arndt says. &lt;em&gt;“We’ve seen a warming trend related to greenhouse gases for four, five, six decades now”&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.npr.org/sections/thetwo-way/2017/01/18/510405739/2016-was-the-hottest-year-yet-scientists-declare&quot;&gt;NPR, Jan 2017&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two graphs that shows the time evolution of globally-averaged temperatues are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nasa.gov/sites/default/files/thumbnails/image/2016gistempupdateblack.gif&quot;&gt;NASA&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2017/01/18/science/earth/2016-hottest-year-on-record.html?_r=0&quot;&gt;New York Times&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information please visit: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nasa.gov/press-release/nasa-noaa-data-show-2016-warmest-year-on-record-globally&quot;&gt;https://www.nasa.gov/press-release/nasa-noaa-data-show-2016-warmest-year-on-record-globally&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jan 2017 20:59:59 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>http://hzambran.github.io/droughts/climate-change/2017/01/19/Year_2016_hottest_on_record.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://hzambran.github.io/droughts/climate-change/2017/01/19/Year_2016_hottest_on_record.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>droughts</category>
        
        <category>climate-change</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Participación en la Conferencia AGU 2016</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;On December 13, 2016, I presented the work titled &lt;a href=&quot;http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.224157&quot;&gt;Disentangling the contribution of precipitation and temperature to Chilean megadrought (20102015)&lt;/a&gt; at the conference &lt;a href=&quot;https://fallmeeting.agu.org/2016/&quot;&gt;American Geophysical Union (AGU) 2016&lt;/a&gt;. In this work I used two drought indices to analyze the contribution of precipitation and temperature to the recent droughts that have affected Chile, in order to improve our understanding about the onset, duration and magnitude of these events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is the first time that a professor with affiliation “Universidad de La Frontera” presents in this conference, the most important of Earth Sciences worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This work is part of a collaborative research that I carry out for the &lt;a href=&quot;www.cr2.cl&quot;&gt;Climate and Resilience Center&lt;/a&gt; of the Universidad de Chile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spanish version&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;El pasado 13 de Diciembre de 2016, presenté el trabajo titulado &lt;a href=&quot;http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.224157&quot;&gt;Disentangling the contribution of precipitation and temperature to Chilean megadrought (20102015)&lt;/a&gt; en la conferencia &lt;a href=&quot;https://fallmeeting.agu.org/2016/&quot;&gt;American Geophysical Union (AGU) 2016&lt;/a&gt;. En este trabajo utilicé dos índices de sequía para analizar la contribución de la precipitación y la temperatura a las recientes sequías que han afectado Chile, para mejorar nuestra comprensión acerca del inicio, duración y magnitud de estos eventos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Es la primera vez que un docente con afiliación Universidad de La Frontera presenta en este evento, el más importante de las Ciencias de la Tierra a nivel mundial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Este trabajo forma parte del trabajo como investigador adjunto que realizo para el &lt;a href=&quot;www.cr2.cl&quot;&gt;Climate and Resilience Center&lt;/a&gt; de la Universidad de Chile.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 13 Dec 2016 20:59:59 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>http://hzambran.github.io/cr2/droughts/fondecyt-11150861/2016/12/13/AGU2016.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://hzambran.github.io/cr2/droughts/fondecyt-11150861/2016/12/13/AGU2016.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>CR2</category>
        
        <category>droughts</category>
        
        <category>fondecyt-11150861</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Expected changes in precipitation and temperature by 2050 (La Tercera)</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A recent study, delivered in July 2016, projected that by 2050 Santiago will have the most extreme variation in temperature of all regional capitals, with 2.7°C, which is 14% higher compared to today. In winter, the increase will be 1.7%, representing an increase of 19%, while precipitation will be reduced by 55 millimeters (mm), 15% less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other regional capitals, as Arica and Copiapó, extreme temperatures rise about 2.2°C are also expected for each summer, but it will be Arica where the temperature will rise more in winter, with 2.5° C.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information please visit: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.latercera.com/noticia/tendencias/2016/09/659-697259-9-informe-climatico-dice-que-a-2050-temperatura-en-santiago-subira-27c-y-lluvias.shtml&quot;&gt;Informe climático dice que a 2050 temperatura en Santiago subirá 2,7°C y lluvias caerán 15%&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 21 Aug 2016 20:59:59 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>http://hzambran.github.io/droughts/climate-change/2016/08/21/Temperature_and_precipitation_changes_by_2050.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://hzambran.github.io/droughts/climate-change/2016/08/21/Temperature_and_precipitation_changes_by_2050.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>droughts</category>
        
        <category>climate-change</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Megadrought expands to southern Chile (La Tercera)</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Today the country is experiencing one of the longest and most geographically extensive droughts in its history, which has nearly eight years in some sectors, and extends from the Coquimbo to the La Araucania region. Experts estimate that in the future these cycles would increase. According to an analysis by the  Center for Climate and Resilience Research (CR2) in 2015, these mega-droughts will become more common, occurring in Chile every 20 years by 2050 if emissions continue to increase greenhouse gases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To date, 17 of the 22 stations of the Meteorological Direction of Chile (DMC) present below normal precipitation amounts. Coyhaique (45ºS) is the one with the most extreme situation. There, the precipitation is around 220 mm, far from normal to date according to the climatological period 1981-2010, which is 884.5 mm, resulting in a deficit of 75%. The level of rainfall is the lowest registration for the area (starting in 1960), although it is projected that in the next three months rains occur within the normal range indicates Catalina Cortes, meteorologist at DMC. However, it should end the year in deficit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information please visit: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.latercera.com/noticia/tendencias/2016/08/659-693246-9-megasequia-se-expande-hacia-el-sur-del-pais.shtml&quot;&gt;Megasequía se expande hacia el sur del país&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 21 Aug 2016 20:59:59 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>http://hzambran.github.io/droughts/climate-change/2016/08/21/Megasequia-se_expande_hacia_el_sur.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://hzambran.github.io/droughts/climate-change/2016/08/21/Megasequia-se_expande_hacia_el_sur.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>droughts</category>
        
        <category>climate-change</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Drought in Puyehue and Rupanco lakes (SoyChile.cl)</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;After &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.australosorno.cl/impresa/2016/06/14/full/cuerpo-principal/2/?utm_source=pagina&amp;amp;utm_campaign=soychile&amp;amp;utm_medium=3&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Austral de Osorno&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; revealed the worrying decline in the water levels of Llanquihue Lake in the  surrounding of Puerto Octay, it was found that is not the only lake basin of the region affected by the lack of rainfall that experts have attributed to climate change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is because now the Rupanco and Puyehue lakes in the province of Osorno, have also shown and alarming and disturbing situation. In the first case, locals say that in some sectors the beach has increased from 20 to 200 meters, and in areas normally covered by water can now move on foot or by vehicle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A similar situation occurs in the Rupanco, where residents also confirm that there is an obvious decline in its water levels, exposing larger portions of land. *This is the year where I’ve seen the worst shortage of water in the lake. It has fallen very little rain. Luckily our pastures are still green, but the lake has suffered,” said a local farmer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information please visit: &lt;a href=&quot;[http://www.soychile.cl/Osorno/Sociedad/2016/06/16/399942/No-es-solo-el-Llanquihue-asi-lucen-los-lagos-Puyehue-y-Rupanco-por-la-sequia.aspx]&quot;&gt;No es sólo el Llanquihue: así lucen los lagos Puyehue y Rupanco por la sequía&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 21 Aug 2016 20:59:59 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>http://hzambran.github.io/droughts/climate-change/2016/08/21/Drought_in_Puyehue_and_Rupanco_lakes.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://hzambran.github.io/droughts/climate-change/2016/08/21/Drought_in_Puyehue_and_Rupanco_lakes.html</guid>
        
        <category>droughts</category>
        
        <category>climate-change</category>
        
        
        <category>droughts</category>
        
        <category>climate-change</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
